Welcome, dear brothers and sisters!
愛する兄弟姉妹 ようこそ！
I’m so happy to share with you this update.
皆さんにお話しできることを
うれしく思います
It has been amazing
to see the Kingdom work move ahead,
このパンデミック中も
王国の活動が前進しているのは
素晴らしいことです
even during this pandemic.
Various branches are reporting all-time peaks
多くの支部は
伝道者の最高数を報告しています
in the number of publishers, pioneers,
開拓者 集会出席者
聖書レッスンの数についても同様です
meeting attendance, and Bible studies.
Many have reported peaks
in the Memorial attendance.
記念式の出席者が最高数になった国も
たくさんあります
For example,
the Philippines branch reported
例えば フィリピン支部の報告によると
that over 739,000
今年の記念式に73万9000人以上が
出席しました
attended the Memorial this year!
That is more than three times
the number of publishers.
これは 伝道者数の3倍以上に当たります
One hundred congregations,
mostly in urban areas,
100の会衆では
主に都市部にある会衆ですが
reported a Memorial attendance
of at least 500.
記念式にそれぞれ500人以上が
出席しました
That means that 50,000 attended the Memorial
ですから この100の会衆だけで
5万人以上が記念式に
出席したことになります
in just those 100 congregations!
In various parts of the earth,
多くの国では 食べ物を手に入れることが
困難になっています
many struggle to obtain food.
With the assistance of hundreds
of Disaster Relief Committees,
私たちは 各地の災害救援
委員会を通して
そうした地域の兄弟姉妹を
援助しています
we continue to help our brothers.
For example,
in Venezuela, each month,
例えば ベネズエラでは
毎月平均130トンの食料を
we are providing
an average of 130 tons of food
2万5000人の困窮した兄弟姉妹に
届けています
to 25,000 brothers in need.
One 90-year-old pioneer sister said:
90歳の開拓者の姉妹は
こう言っています
“I know that the aid comes from Jehovah,
「助けてくださっているエホバに
感謝しています
“but he uses brothers
that I do not even know,
エホバは 会ったこともない兄弟たちを
通して助けてくれています
“and yet they love me and help me.
兄弟たちは親身になって
援助してくれます
Thank you, dear family.”
兄弟姉妹 本当にありがとうございます」
It is heartwarming
to see how Jehovah is helping
うれしいことに エホバは
ベネズエラの兄弟姉妹を助けています
our brothers and sisters in Venezuela
and around the globe.
世界各地の兄弟姉妹のこともです
We thank all of you for making that possible
こうした援助ができるのは
皆さんの惜しみない寄付のおかげです
by means of your donations.
In our last Governing Body Update,{
前回の「統治体からの話」で
ハード兄弟は その時までに
「世界中のベテル家族の
that “about 50 percent
of the worldwide Bethel family
約50パーセントがワクチンの接種を
終え」たと述べていました
have been vaccinated so far.”
Initially, it seemed impossible
to obtain vaccines
当初 ある国々ではワクチンを
入手することが不可能に思えました
in some countries of the world.
But it has been amazing to see
でも驚くべきことに 今では
世界中のベテル家族の80パーセント以上
that now more than 80 percent
of our worldwide Bethel family
つまり1万9000人以上のベテル奉仕者が
ワクチンの接種を終えています
—that is, more than 19,000 Bethelites—
are vaccinated,
and we are doing what we can
to assist the branch offices
私たちは まだワクチンを
入手できていない支部事務所を
that have not been able to obtain vaccines.
援助するため ベストを尽くしています
As you know,
by keeping the Bethel family safe,
ベテル家族の安全を
確保することによって
we protect the flow of spiritual food
信仰を強める食物が
途絶えることなく供給され
and support spiritual activities worldwide.
世界中の活動をサポートする
ことができています
On behalf of the Governing Body,
パンデミック中 全ての取り決めに
快く協力してくださっている兄弟姉妹に
thank you, dear brothers and sisters,
for your tremendous cooperation
統治体を代表して
心からの感謝をお伝えします
with all the arrangements
during the pandemic.
There have been many adjustments
in a short time,
短い期間にさまざまな
調整がありましたが
but you have done so well.
本当によく協力してくださいました
We truly love you for your fine spirit
皆さんを心から愛しています
皆さんは私たちと「肩を並べて」
働いてくださっています
in working “shoulder to shoulder” with us.
While we all have had changes in our routine,
私たちの生活は
いろいろな面で変化しました
some of our circuit overseers
who serve in foreign lands
特に大きな変化を経験したのは
外国で奉仕している巡回監督です
have had major changes.
They had to return to their home countries
during the pandemic.
パンデミック中 故国に
帰らなければならなかった人もいます
Even so, some continue to serve
それでもZoomを通して
割り当てられた巡回区で
引き続き奉仕している人たちもいます
the congregations in their circuits via Zoom,
despite being in a different country
国境や時差を越えて
奉仕を続けています
and in a different time zone.
Let’s hear from one.
1組の夫婦にお聞きしましょう
A few months into the pandemic,
パンデミックになって間もなく
父の健康状態が悪化しました
my father’s health was failing.
So we made the decision
それで 母をサポートするため
米国に戻ることにしました
to return to the States
and assist my mother.
Although in the beginning
we didn’t think we’d be here so long,
最初は 米国での滞在がこれほど長くなる
とは思っていませんでしたが
it turned out that the surge in the pandemic
パンデミックのせいで
prevented us from going back
to our assignment in the circuit in Bolivia.
ボリビアの巡回区に戻ることが
できませんでした
Well, being displaced,
we just weren’t sure
ボリビアに戻れない状態で
巡回区での奉仕をきちんと行えるのか
正直不安でした
if we were going to be able to serve
and complete our assignment effectively.
We felt that we needed to make
必要な調整を行って 正しい見方を
持てるようにする必要があると思いました
the necessary adjustments
to have the right attitude.
So fervent prayer really helped us
to get the right mindset.
正しい考え方をするために
熱烈な祈りが助けになりました
And being able to see
how Jehovah answered those prayers
エホバが私の祈りを
よく聞いてくださったので
本当に信仰が強まりました
is very faith-strengthening.
Jehovah is blessing this arrangement.
エホバの祝福を感じています
It’s the arrangement
that has been put in place,
組織がこういう取り決めを
設けてくれたので 十分に活用しています
and it’s what we’re using.
We’re making the best of it.
But we’re having success
because Jehovah is behind it.
でも うまくいっているのは
エホバのおかげです
We’ve had brothers who are now qualified
パンデミック中に進歩して 伝道者になる
資格を身に付けた人たちもいます
to be publishers
—unbaptized publishers.
There are brothers
who’ve dedicated their lives
中には 献身して
バプテスマを受けた人たちもいます
and gotten baptized during this pandemic.
One brother in particular
has so much enthusiasm for phone witnessing
ある兄弟は 電話伝道を
とても熱心に行っています
that last month he was able
to report over 100 return visits,
先月 再訪問を100件以上行い
いろいろな人に200回以上
ビデオを見せることができました
and he was able to show
over 200 videos to different ones.
One Bible student loves her study so much,
and also attending meetings,
ある女性は 聖書をとても熱心に学び
集会にも出席しています
that she’s willing to walk one hour each way
聖書レッスンをしたり
集会に出席したりするために
in order to have a good signal on her phone
電波のよく入る所まで
1時間もかけて歩いていっています
so that she can tie in to her study
and also to the meetings.
Throughout this past year,
過去1年 エホバは決して
私たちを見捨てたりしませんでした
I’ve learned that Jehovah has never left us.
He’s been in total control
of every situation.
全ての状況を完全に把握しています
He’s been able to direct
his organization, his people,
エホバは ご自分の民や組織が
何をすべきかを
exactly to the place that we need to be.
はっきりと教えてくれています
This has all been proof
that Jehovah will never abandon us.
エホバが私たちを
決して見捨てたりしないことの
強力な証拠です
How encouraging to hear how our brothers
本当に励まされます
このような状況の中でも
are remaining united and spiritually active!
兄弟たちは一致して
熱心に活動しています
But we do have to continue
to guard our unity.
私たちはこの一致を守りたいと思います
What is unity?
一致とは何ですか
It has been defined as “oneness,”
「一つであること」とか
「調和した状態」と定義されています
“a condition of harmony.”
Note how the apostle Paul describes our role
一致を保つため
私たちは何をしなければなりませんか
in maintaining unity at Ephesians 4:3.
パウロがエフェソス 4:3で
述べていることに注目しましょう
There we read:
こうあります
「平和という絆で結ばれ，
“earnestly endeavoring to maintain
聖なる力による一致を保つよう
真剣に努力してください」
“the oneness of the spirit
in the uniting bond of peace.”
Note that it takes effort
to maintain our unity.
一致というのは
努力して保つ必要があります
Paul said that we must “earnestly endeavor,”
パウロが述べた通り
「真剣に努力」する必要があるのです
or work hard, at it.
What could pose a danger to our unity?
どんなものが
一致を脅かす恐れがありますか
What if we
became too emotionally involved
賛否両論のある問題に
あまりにも深入りするなら
in issues that are divisive?
どうなるでしょうか
The Bible foretold at 2 Timothy chapter 3
テモテ第二 3章では 人々が
「自分を愛し⋯⋯全く人に
that men would be “lovers of themselves,
同意しようとせず⋯⋯乱暴」に
なることが予告されていました
“. . . not open to any agreement,
. . . [and] fierce.”
We see this in the world today.
今の世界はまさにそうなっています
People are “not open to any agreement.”
人々は「全く⋯⋯同意しようと
［しません］」
They quickly become “fierce,”
すぐに「乱暴」になります
taking strong positions
on all types of issues.
いろいろな問題について
強い意見を主張します
As Christians,
we are “no part of [the] world.”
私たちクリスチャンは
「この世界のものでは［ない］」ので
そういう議論に関わりません
We stay out of those debates.
For example,
who would have thought
例えば私たちは 感染を防ぐために
マスクをすることが議論になるなどとは
that wearing a mask
to prevent the spread of disease
考えもしませんでした
could become an issue?
From the time when we were little children,
私たちが子供の頃から親は
せきやくしゃみをするときには
our parents taught us to cover our mouth
口を覆うように と教えてくれました
when we coughed or sneezed.
In his precious Word,
聖書にも 病気が広がるのを防ぐための
さまざまな予防策が記されています
Jehovah outlined many practical measures
that would prevent the spread of disease.
So how could wearing a mask
become controversial for some?
では マスクをするかどうかが
問題になるのはなぜですか
Where is that thinking coming from?
そういう考えは
どこから来ているのでしょうか
We have to be careful.
私たちは注意しなければなりません
All of us are exposed to worldly thinking
テレビや インターネットや 職場や 学校で
世の考え方にさらされているからです
on television, on the Internet,
at work, or at school.
There are many websites
that promote conspiracy theories.
陰謀論を広めるウェブサイトも
たくさんあります
If we’re not careful,
注意しないと 私たちもそうした情報に
振り回されてしまうかもしれません
we could become emotionally involved
in these debates.
We could allow ourselves to be guided
by “the voice of strangers”
私たちは 「知らない人⋯⋯の声」ではなく
エホバが用いている
instead of listening to Jehovah’s channel,
「忠実で思慮深い奴隷」に
従う必要があります
“the faithful and discreet slave.”
As we face the end of this system of things,
このことは 終わりが近い今 特に重要です
this will become more and more essential
エホバとの絆を保ち
間違った情報に惑わされないためです
to our safety and spirituality.
That’s why we appreciate
you dear brothers and sisters so much.
この点で私たちは
兄弟姉妹に深く感謝しています
As soon as you discern that Jehovah’s spirit
皆さんはエホバの聖なる力が
is directing the Governing Body
to go in a certain way,
統治体をある方向に導いていることに
気付くとすぐに それに従っています
you are quick to follow.
And as a result, we enjoy precious unity.
その結果 私たちは一致していられます
This reminds me
of the Bible example of Naaman.
聖書に記されている
ナアマンの例を思い出します
Through a messenger,
the prophet Elisha told Naaman
預言者エリシャは 使者を通して
ナアマンにこう伝えました
he would be healed from his leprosy
「ヨルダン川で7回体を洗えば
重い皮膚病が治ります」
if he bathed seven times in the Jordan River.
How did Naaman react?
ナアマンはどうするでしょうか
Let’s read together
ご一緒に 列王第二 5:11, 12を
読んでみましょう
2 Kings 5:11, 12:
“At this Naaman became indignant
「するとナアマンは憤慨し
立ち去ろうとして言った
“and started to leave, saying:
“‘Here I said to myself,
『私は 「彼が私の所に出てきてここに立ち
彼の神エホバの名を呼んで
“‘“He will come out to me and stand here
“‘“and call on the name of Jehovah his God,
手を患部の上で前後に動かして
治すのだろう」と思っていた
“‘“moving his hand back and forth
“‘over the leprosy to cure it.”
“‘Are not the Abanah and the Pharpar,
ダマスカスのアバナ川や
ファルパル川の方が イスラエルの
どの川よりもいいではないか
“‘the rivers of Damascus,
“‘better than all the waters of Israel?
それらの川で体を洗うのでは
清くなれないのか』
“Can I not wash in them and become clean?’
With that he turned and went away in a rage.”
こうして彼は向きを変え
怒りながら去っていった」
Naaman had his own idea
ナアマンは エリシャが
どのように病気を治すのか
about how he was going to be cured.
勝手なイメージを持っていました
強く思い込んでいたのです
He felt strongly about it.
But Jehovah had a different idea.
でも エホバの考えは違いました
To be cured,
ナアマンは治してもらうために
Naaman would have to humble himself
謙遜になって
エホバの預言者の指示に
従わなければなりませんでした
and follow direction from Jehovah’s channel.
Naaman was struggling,
ナアマンは従おうとはしませんでしたが
家来たちは違いました
but his servants got the point.
What did they tell him to do?
ナアマンに何と言いましたか
どんな結果になったでしょうか
And what was the result?
Let’s read verses 13 and 14:
13, 14節を読んでみましょう
“His servants now approached him and said:
「すると家来たちが
ナアマンに近寄ってこう言った
“‘My father, if the prophet had told you
『ご主人さま あの預言者から
何か大変なことをするように
言われたとしても
“‘to do something extraordinary,
その通りになさるのではありませんか
“‘would you not do it?
“‘How much more, then, since he
彼はただ 「体を洗って 清くなりなさい」
と言ったのですから
“only said to you, “Wash and be clean”?’
そうしてもよいのではありませんか』
それでナアマンは行って
“At that he went down
“and plunged into the Jordan seven times,
真の神に遣わされた人に言われた通り
ヨルダン川に７回体を浸した
“according to the word
“of the man of the true God.
“Then his flesh was restored
すると 彼の肌は元に戻って
少年の肌のようになり 清くなった」
“like the flesh of a little boy,
and he became clean.”
Do we get the point?
何を学べますか
Like Naaman,
we might struggle a bit at times,
私たちも指示に従いにくく
感じることがあるかもしれません
especially if we have
our own strong viewpoint.
強い意見を持っているときは
特にそうです
But one thing is certain:
でも確かなことがあります
If we follow direction
coming from Jehovah’s channel,
エホバが用いている人たちの指示に
従うなら 祝福され
we will be blessed
さらに大切なこととして
一致していられるのです
and, more important,
we will remain united.
もちろん悪魔は このことを
うれしく思っていません
Of course, the Devil is not happy
to see this cooperation
—this beautiful unity that we enjoy—
私たちが一致しているのが
気に入らないのです
so we have to be on guard
so as to maintain it.
ですから 一致を守るために
努力しなければなりません
This reminds me of an event in my life,
many years ago,
ずいぶん前のことになりますが
この一致を守ることに関して
忘れられない経験があります
when this lesson was impressed on my mind.
At that time,
some of the brothers did become divided
当時 一部の兄弟たちが
組織を離れてしまったため
and it led to so many problems.
さまざまな問題が生じました
You may remember
その出来事を取り上げたビデオを
覚えておられるかもしれません
that we had a video about those events.
Let’s watch a clip from that video.
その一部を見てみましょう
A lot of pressure was
on the brothers in Romania.
状況が特に難しかったのは
ルーマニアです
The Communist Party tried
共産党は兄弟たちの間に
不信の種をまこうとしました
to sow distrust among the brothers,
別々に兄弟たちに会い
meeting with them separately
一方にはあることを伝え
and telling some brothers one thing
and telling other brothers something else.
他方にはまた違うことを伝えました
Sometimes it happened
時には当局者が真理に
関心がある人のふりをし
that an official posed
as an interested person
and was clever enough to disguise that
兄弟たちをだまして
進歩しているかのように見せました
and pretend to make progress in the truth
バプテスマを受けただけでなく
—not only to the point of getting baptized
長老にさえなった人もいます
but even to the point of becoming an elder.
でも実際は 組織の全体を
探り出すことを目的とした
But he was in reality
an agent of the secret police
秘密警察の工作員だったのです
with an aim to find out everything
about the organization.
その影響で ある兄弟たちは
So it did lead to, in one case,
本部によって任命された兄弟に
対する不信感を募らせていき
the brothers starting to distrust someone
結果として エホバが用いておられる
組織から離れていきました
that was actually appointed by headquarters.
And these brothers then separated
from the organization that Jehovah used,
ある人たちは数年はおろか
何十年も離れてしまいました
and some of them were separated
for not just a few years but for decades.
そうした人たちは大勢いて
5000人ほどもいました
And they were a large number,
up to 5,000 publishers.
その人たちも集まり続け
They continued to meet together.
伝道もしていましたが
以前から持っていた資料
だけでそうしていました
They were preaching and using material
that they had left over from earlier years,
but they hardly got any new material to study
本部が用いる組織とは
接触を断っていたので
because they were not in touch
with the organization
新しい研究用の資料は何も
手に入れられませんでした
that was used by headquarters.
Attempts to bring the brothers back
into the organization
離れた人たちが組織に
戻れるようにする試みは
were made from time to time,
度々行なわれましたが
but it seemed that the brothers
from the separated organization
彼らはまだ兄弟たちを十分に
信頼していないようでした
did not have sufficient trust.
But when we presented
しかし 離れたグループのリーダーに
統治体の成員の一人が
来ることを伝えると
to the leader of the separated group
that one from the Governing Body would come,
それなら信頼できるということで
兄弟たちが再び1つになるための
he was happy about that
and he had enough trust in that case
真剣な話し合いを持つ
ことに喜んで応じました
to agree that we should have a meeting
離れたグループからは
リーダーであるアルブ兄弟と
and seriously talk about reunification.
主だった長老たち4人が参加しました
And so from the separated group,
there were Brother Albu, who was the leader,
わたしたちの側は
ジャラズ兄弟と通訳
and four of his main elders.
And from our side,
わたし そしてルーマニアの国内
委員会の代表者たちがいました
there was Brother Jaracz, our translator,
and I was part of that group.
Also, there were
several from the Country Committee of Romania.
最初の日の夜 彼らは兄弟たちに
対する非難をたくさん述べました
I remember that the first night
険悪な雰囲気でしたが
わたしたちは耳を傾けました
there were a lot of accusations
about what the others had done or not done,
which did not create the best spirit,
でも 別の夜に会合を持つこと
にはみな同意しました
and we mainly listened.
But everybody agreed to meet another night.
2日目の夜 エホバが彼らに
戻って来て欲しいと
And the second night,
Jehovah obviously wanted
願っておられることが
明らかになりました
the brothers to unite again
彼らの態度が全く変わっており
because the whole spirit was different,
全てを話して誤解を解いたからです
and the brothers talked the matters over
and clarified some misunderstandings.
その日の終わり アルブ兄弟が
こう言ったのを今でも覚えています
And at the end of the second evening,
I remember
「もう一度１つになろう
that the leader of the separated group,
Brother Albu, said,
いま組織に戻らなければ
‘Let’s do it because if we don’t do it now,
二度とチャンスはないかもしれない」
we may never have another opportunity again.’
こうして戻ることを決定したのです
And so the decision was made.
1日で5000人の兄弟たちが
組織に戻ってくるなんて･･･
That doesn’t happen every day
that 5,000 brothers
come back to the organization.
その時から 再び1つになるために
全てのことが組織されました
From then on,
all the practical things
彼らにはわたしたちの会衆に
加わることが求められました
were put in place
to accomplish this reunification.
They were asked to merge
with our congregations.
それはとても謙遜さがいることでしたが
彼らは喜んでそうしました
And that also took
a lot of humility on their part,
兄弟たちは本当に誠実であり
but they were willing to do it.
So they were really brothers
真理を愛していたのです
こうして兄弟たちは再び1つになり
in their heart
and loved the truth.
これはサタンに対するエホバの
素晴らしい勝利となりました
And so the reunification was accomplished,
and that was a wonderful victory for Jehovah
and against Satan.
ルーマニアの兄弟たちの
経験を振り返ると
不完全な人間の間では常に
誤解が生じ得ることや
Reflecting on the experience
with the brothers in Romania,
we can see
that there could always be
misunderstandings among humans
責任を担っている
兄弟たちの間違いによって
正当な不満さえ抱きかねない
ことがよく分かります
and there could always be
even legitimate complaints
でも大切なのは
about the misconduct
of some responsible brothers.
これがエホバの組織であることへの
信頼を決して失わないことです
But the important thing is
エホバが祝福しておられる組織です
never to lose trust
that this is Jehovah’s organization.
全てをご覧になっています
That’s where Jehovah’s blessing is.
エホバは聖霊を用いて
組織を一致させておられ
Jehovah sees it all.
Jehovah uses his holy spirit
望むことを成し遂げられる方です
to keep the organization together,
わたしたちが聖霊と共に働くなら
and what he wants to have accomplished
will happen.
エホバはその努力を祝福して成功させ
If we work with the holy spirit,
then Jehovah will bless our efforts
こうしてエホバに賛美が
もたらされるのです
and it will be successful to his praise.
Of course,
these challenges were not unique
このような問題を経験したのは
ルーマニアの兄弟たち
だけではありません
to the brothers in Romania.
Similar challenges
occurred in other countries
同じようなことが
鉄のカーテンの向こうの
他の国々でも起きていました
that were behind the Iron Curtain,
including Czechoslovakia,
Russia, and Ukraine.
チェコスロバキア ロシア
ウクライナなどです
So, what have we learned in this update?
皆さんは この話から何を学びましたか
Jehovah’s organization is on the move.
エホバの組織は 今も前進しています
Even during this pandemic,
このパンデミック中も
we see strong evidence
that Jehovah’s spirit is blessing
良い知らせを伝え
人々を弟子とする活動を
エホバが祝福し
前進させていることは明らかです
and moving ahead
the preaching and disciple-making work.
Despite many challenges,
you dear brothers and sisters
皆さんはさまざまな問題と闘いながら
一致を保つために真剣に努力しています
are working hard
to maintain our precious unity.
As a result,
we are enjoying a spiritual paradise
その結果 私たちは愛にあふれた
平和な兄弟関係を楽しんでいます
as we work unitedly together.
Satan will continue to try
to stir up division,
サタンはこれからも
人々を分裂させようとするでしょう
even among Jehovah’s people.
エホバの民のこともです
What can we do
to successfully resist his efforts?
どうすればサタンの攻撃に
抵抗することができますか
Listen to the channel that Jehovah is using,
耳を傾けるべきなのは
エホバが用いている
「忠実で思慮深い奴隷」の声です
“the faithful and discreet slave.”
Don’t allow yourself
to become emotionally involved
世の中ではいろいろなことが
議論の対象になっていますが
with the causes of this world,
whatever they may be.
そうしたものに
振り回されないようにしてください
There is no doubt
that Jehovah will richly bless
王イエス･キリストを支持し
イエスが今用いている
「忠実で思慮深い奴隷」に
all those who support our King, Jesus Christ,
協力している人全てを エホバは必ず
祝福してくださることでしょう
and the channel that he is using today,
“the faithful and discreet slave.”
From the World Headquarters
of Jehovah’s Witnesses,
エホバの証人の世界本部から
JW Broadcasting®でした
this is JW Broadcasting®.